<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.0.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-09-14T00:09:41+10:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">andy luu</title><subtitle></subtitle><entry><title type="html">Sydney’s sandstone</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/architecture/2020/09/13/sandstone.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Sydney's sandstone" /><published>2020-09-13T17:19:03+10:00</published><updated>2020-09-13T17:19:03+10:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/architecture/2020/09/13/sandstone</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/architecture/2020/09/13/sandstone.html">&lt;p&gt;As a project manager in the construction field, you encounter a lot of interesting topics that you would otherwise never know about. I’ve summarised some really interesting things about sandstone that I learned via a report authored by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.jasperswann.com.au/stonemason/&quot;&gt;Jasper Swann&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-does-sydneys-sandstone-achieve-its-look&quot;&gt;How does Sydney’s sandstone achieve its look?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The sandstone that you typically see on historic sandstone buildings in Sydney CBD has historically been known as &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sydney_sandstone&quot;&gt;Yellowblock&lt;/a&gt;. It actually comes out of the ground with a pale grey-to-white colour but develops the honey/pale-brown colour that it’s known for via an oxidation process where minerals within the stone migrate to the surface and react on exposure to the atmosphere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;why-is-there-so-much-variety-in-colour&quot;&gt;Why is there so much variety in colour?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://images.squarespace-cdn.com/content/v1/5381e632e4b024bd858030cd/1517973793547-KC1NHVZT397IQ0398LBV/ke17ZwdGBToddI8pDm48kLkXF2pIyv_F2eUT9F60jBl7gQa3H78H3Y0txjaiv_0fDoOvxcdMmMKkDsyUqMSsMWxHk725yiiHCCLfrh8O1z4YTzHvnKhyp6Da-NYroOW3ZGjoBKy3azqku80C789l0iyqMbMesKd95J-X4EagrgU9L3Sa3U8cogeb0tjXbfawd0urKshkc5MgdBeJmALQKw/Hilton+Sydney-+Piles+creek+Cream+sawn+Curved+cladding+1+%284%29.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
If you look at any Yellowblock sandstone in Sydney you’ll notice colour variations ranging from dark brown all the way to orange. This process depends on the process of siderite, which varies in concentration in any given party of the quarry, which leads to unpredictable levels of colouration in the sandstone. Other minerals such as manganese present in varying quantities can also contribution to the sandstone developing a darker/browner colouration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;why-is-this-an-issue&quot;&gt;Why is this an issue?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This process can occur anywhere from days and weeks to months after quarrying and can continue for years. Although stone is a natural product and some level of variety in colour/texture can always be expected, there could be substantial colour variations deviating strongly from the design intent that couldn’t be picked up at the time of installation. That said, there is already a significant level of colour variation in many existing installations through Sydney CBD and this does not detract from the colour appearance of the building as a whole.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-can-you-do-if-you-want-to-minimise-the-colour-variation&quot;&gt;What can you do if you want to minimise the colour variation?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are also options available to intentionally alter the surface colour of sandstone that have long been used by suppliers and stonemasons:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Acid wash with 2% Hydrochrolic Acid
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;This has the effect of removing any brown/grey discolouration due to manganese which leaves allows a relatively uniform golden colouration to develop&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Ideally you could allow the sandstone to all develop naturally and acid wash any significantly discoloured pieces, but the process is much easier to carry out at installation when scaffolding is available&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Application of a chemical colouring agent
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;This has the effect of causing a permanent golden colouration of the surface of the sandstone and is used to add colour to stones that have failed to self-oxidise&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">As a project manager in the construction field, you encounter a lot of interesting topics that you would otherwise never know about. I’ve summarised some really interesting things about sandstone that I learned via a report authored by Jasper Swann.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">CS Fundamentals</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/learning/cs/2020/09/06/csfundamentals.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="CS Fundamentals" /><published>2020-09-06T17:19:03+10:00</published><updated>2020-09-06T17:19:03+10:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/learning/cs/2020/09/06/csfundamentals</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/learning/cs/2020/09/06/csfundamentals.html">&lt;p&gt;I had my first CS interview (albeit on a smaller scale) the other day and I think I let myself down. I probably should’ve spent more time studying CS fundamentals and less time studying networking or &lt;a href=&quot;https://andyluu.com/learning/cs/2020/08/30/understandingRPL.html&quot;&gt;RPL&lt;/a&gt;. In hindsight it’s definitely something that I should understand well before going into any CS interview. The key areas that I needed to work on further were:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;1-sorting&quot;&gt;1. Sorting&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The different sorting algorithms had appeared in multiple different courses that I had done, but there were a few gaps in my knowledge:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Quicksort&lt;/strong&gt;: 
  I’d watched a lecture about quicksort, but my recollection boiled down to “partition the array into smaller sub-arrays that get recursively sorted” (why is it even called quicksort? what if someone finds a quicker sorting algorithm one day? why not call it something more descriptive like pivotsort or partitionsort?). After watching a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=XE4VP_8Y0BU&amp;amp;t=1s&quot;&gt;few&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Hoixgm4-P4M&quot;&gt;YouTube&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=x2LEyLvW0Lw&quot;&gt;explanations&lt;/a&gt; I wrote up an implementation in Python which hopefully solidifies quicksort in my mind.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Why use one sorting algorithm over another?&lt;/strong&gt;: At the very least the name is a good reminder that quicksort is on average faster than mergesort, but I didn’t know why. &lt;strong&gt;Short answer&lt;/strong&gt;: The constant factors of nlogn are smaller. &lt;strong&gt;Long answer:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://cs.stackexchange.com/questions/3/why-is-quicksort-better-than-other-sorting-algorithms-in-practice&quot;&gt;probably not worth remembering.&lt;/a&gt;. I remembered that insertion sort is better than mergesort / quicksort for small n, but forgot what situations bubble sort is useful in (when the array is mostly sorted already)&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;2-time-and-space-complexity&quot;&gt;2. Time and Space Complexity&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There’s some overlap with sorting here in the understanding of why one algorithm is better than another but that’s easy to remember and something I got mostly right anyway. What I need to work on here is the fundamental skill of reading some code or considering different solutions to a problem and figuring out in your head what the time and space complexity is.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I think it’s something that I’m actually okay at, but during the interview I know I rarely felt 100% confident about it. To some extent I think doing heaps and heaps of Leetcode problems and evaluating the solutions will help here. A related skill that I’ve never really thought about and I think will be useful is the ability to look at a problem and come up with different solutions based on different requirements e.g. constant space.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;3-arrays-linked-lists-and-memory&quot;&gt;3. Arrays, Linked Lists and Memory&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://andyluu.com/jekyll/update/2020/05/31/learning-the-basics.html&quot;&gt;CS50 Introduction to Computer Science&lt;/a&gt; had some great coverage of these topics in the context of C, but my time with that course was almost a year ago and definitely needed some revision. I had an okay time with remembering how fast they could get values, set values, add values etc. but I mixed them up pretty easily. It’s definitely a better idea to remember how these operations actually work at a low level and then I can determine the time complexity on my own.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All in all, I’m really glad I experienced my first CS interview in a fairly low-pressure environment. Even though I think I performed pretty poorly it was a good indication of the gaps in my knowledge and interview preparation and I’m going to be in a much better spot whenever my next CS interview is!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I had my first CS interview (albeit on a smaller scale) the other day and I think I let myself down. I probably should’ve spent more time studying CS fundamentals and less time studying networking or RPL. In hindsight it’s definitely something that I should understand well before going into any CS interview. The key areas that I needed to work on further were:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Understanding RPL</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/learning/cs/2020/08/30/understandingRPL.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Understanding RPL" /><published>2020-08-30T17:19:03+10:00</published><updated>2020-08-30T17:19:03+10:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/learning/cs/2020/08/30/understandingRPL</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/learning/cs/2020/08/30/understandingRPL.html">&lt;p&gt;For an upcoming potential job it was suggested that I do some reading on RPL (Routing Protocol for Low-Power and Lossy Networks). Half an hour of reading later, I was still thoroughly perplexed on what all the terms or concepts even meant! Clearly it was time to do my very first networking course.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The OSSU curriculum includes an &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PLEAYkSg4uSQ2dr0XO_Nwa5OcdEcaaELSG&quot;&gt;Introduction to Computer Networking&lt;/a&gt; course, which strangely links to a YouTube playlist of two guys sitting on a couch. From what I can gather the videos are from a Stanford course that was originally available but the Lagunita online learning platform was retired earlier this year. The two alternatives I saw recommended were a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.udacity.com/course/computer-networking--ud436&quot;&gt;Georgia Tech Udacity course&lt;/a&gt; and a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.coursera.org/learn/computer-networking&quot;&gt;Google Coursera course&lt;/a&gt;, more advanced and less advanced than the Stanford course respectively.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I followed both the Stanford and Coursera at first, but I found that the Coursera course had a smoother difficulty curve with more production value as well, and ultimately stayed with that one. As I had limited time, I focused on the basic topics such as the internet layer model, TCP, packet switching, encapsulation and error detection, before skipping ahead to learning about ethernet and wireless networking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Equipped with my new knowledge, I returned for a second attempt at understanding RPL, which I actually found much easier this time around. Here’s my attempt at simplifying the information as much as possible:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;acronyms&quot;&gt;Acronyms&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;DODAG - Destination Oriented Directed Acyclic Graph (has a root and no cycles)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;DIS - DODAG Information Solicitation (solicits information from other nodes)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;DIO - DODAG Information Object (information sent downstream to other nodes)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;DAO - Destination Advertistment Object (provides destination information upwards)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;trickle-timer&quot;&gt;Trickle timer&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;When a node’s data does not agree with its neighbours it communicates quickly to resolve the inconsistency. When they agree, they slow communication exponentially.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;joining&quot;&gt;Joining&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A node that wants to join a network will transmit periodic DISs&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Neighbouring nodes reset their trickle timer in response and send out DIOs more often&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Joining node receives DIOs and probes links with neighbours to select preferred parent with shortest link to the root&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Node registers itself via a DAO that is sent to the parent and forwarded until it reaches the root&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Node receives a DAO-ACK, is not part of the network and starts advertising DIOs in turn on a trickle timer&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;dag-maintenance&quot;&gt;DAG Maintenance&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Nodes constantly probe neighbours to maintain updated link estimates&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Keeps preferred parent up to date e.g. if the link between a node and its parent becomes bad, the node may switch parents&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;When a node finds no more suitable parents it will let its children know it’s no longer a valid parent and then leave the network after a delay&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Meanwhile it starts sending perioding DIS again hoping to discover a new usable parent&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next step: try and explain to concepts above to someone!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">For an upcoming potential job it was suggested that I do some reading on RPL (Routing Protocol for Low-Power and Lossy Networks). Half an hour of reading later, I was still thoroughly perplexed on what all the terms or concepts even meant! Clearly it was time to do my very first networking course.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">How do I structure my Flutter code?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/learning/cs/2020/08/23/flutter4.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How do I structure my Flutter code?" /><published>2020-08-23T17:19:03+10:00</published><updated>2020-08-23T17:19:03+10:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/learning/cs/2020/08/23/flutter4</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/learning/cs/2020/08/23/flutter4.html">&lt;p&gt;This is Part 4 of my posts about learning Flutter. Click here for &lt;a href=&quot;https://andyluu.com/learning/cs/2020/07/19/flutter.html&quot;&gt;Part 1&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://andyluu.com/learning/cs/2020/08/10/flutter2.html&quot;&gt;Part 2&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://andyluu.com/learning/cs/2020/08/16/flutter3.html&quot;&gt;Part 3&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the notifications and settings functionality finished, I wanted to do some cleanup of my code as well as deciding whether I wanted to implement any more features. Up to this point, I wrote all my code in one big Dart file, and while that made everything work smoothly - I felt pretty bad about my very long and very disorganised code. How do I structure my code? How do you know what deserves it’s own seperate file? What’s the correct way to refactor my code? They’re questions that have been on my mind for a while, but I’ve never had to chance to tackle because I’ve never written code at this scale before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There doesn’t seem to be a single correct answer to those questions. Feedback from my friends include:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Get it working first and then refactor&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Follow your intuition&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Split out when the existing file gets too big / annoying to navigate&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Avoid creating classes where possible&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Delete as much code as possible to achieve a simpler / more concise way to write something&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Trial and error&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m definitely on the get it working first and then refactor later boat, and I think that it’s something that I’ll just improve at as I write more code and become more experienced. The process I ended up going through was:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Split the files by functionality. I had a separate file for each ‘page’ of my app, a file for the notification functionality, and a file for parsing the API call. If I had to take it any further, I’d split the frontend and backend code as well, but for a project of this size I think it’s fine as is.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Refactor all my global mutable variables. The majority of these were simple but it was complicated by the requirement for the callbackDispatcher function of the notifications package to be a top-level function and my very clunky implementation of displaying a text forecast.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Simplify my code. Went through and simplified the egregious code at first. Also showed my code to a friend who pointed out a few opportunities for improvement. He also pointed out some code that is probably good enough for a project of this scale, but really should be written another way. I think its good to get in the habit of writing that higher quality code even if it technically doesn’t matter.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s already a lot better than it used to be, but I think there’s still room for improvement. I’m going to take it to a state that I’m happy with and then call this project closed.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">This is Part 4 of my posts about learning Flutter. Click here for Part 1, Part 2 and Part 3.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Making a Settings page on Flutter</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/learning/cs/2020/08/16/flutter3.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Making a Settings page on Flutter" /><published>2020-08-16T17:19:03+10:00</published><updated>2020-08-16T17:19:03+10:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/learning/cs/2020/08/16/flutter3</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/learning/cs/2020/08/16/flutter3.html">&lt;p&gt;This is Part 3 of my posts about learning Flutter. Click here for &lt;a href=&quot;https://andyluu.com/learning/cs/2020/07/19/flutter.html&quot;&gt;Part 1&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://andyluu.com/learning/cs/2020/08/10/flutter2.html&quot;&gt;Part 2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After getting over the unexpectedly tall mountain that was notifications, I wanted to finish the other main functionality - the settings page where the user could change things like:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;their location&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the threshold of rain probability to receive a notification&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the period of time to check for rain&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the time they should receive a notification&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Flutter has a &lt;a href=&quot;https://pub.dev/packages/shared_preferences&quot;&gt;Shared Preferences&lt;/a&gt; package that provides persistant storage for simple data (which allows settings to be saved) but in my search I found the &lt;a href=&quot;https://pub.dev/packages/preferences&quot;&gt;Preferences&lt;/a&gt; package which takes it a step further and helps you generate a settings page with a selection of pre-built widgets. This was so easy that I could do it without ever needing to figure out how to use the shared preferences package, but I wanted the Settings page to function a certain way requiring an auto-completing Google Location search, as well as Sliders and RangeSliders which weren’t implemented in the package.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other pre-built widgets were an ideal starting point for writing my own, and only needed a few tweaks to get working. On the plus side this was also a really easy way to learn how it used the Shared Preferences package to achieve the ability to save settings (easier than reading the README!) - I ended up using the Shared Preferences package elsewhere in my code so that was useful. The Sliders and RangeSliders were pretty trivial to write up, but the auto-completing Google Location search was more complicated than it should’ve been because of how confusing Google Cloud Console is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m pretty happy with how it’s come out but I’ll still need to implement a feature so that a prompt appears when the app is first installed that redirects the user to the settings page.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://firebasestorage.googleapis.com/v0/b/firescript-577a2.appspot.com/o/imgs%2Fapp%2FAndyNotes%2FjoZHmDynNl.png?alt=media&amp;amp;token=b0af3cf5-01e8-463b-86b2-71f688705354&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">This is Part 3 of my posts about learning Flutter. Click here for Part 1 and Part 2</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Figuring out Flutter notifications</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/learning/cs/2020/08/10/flutter2.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Figuring out Flutter notifications" /><published>2020-08-10T17:19:03+10:00</published><updated>2020-08-10T17:19:03+10:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/learning/cs/2020/08/10/flutter2</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/learning/cs/2020/08/10/flutter2.html">&lt;p&gt;This is Part 2 of my posts about learning Flutter. For Part 1 see my &lt;a href=&quot;https://andyluu.com/learning/cs/2020/07/19/flutter.html&quot;&gt;post about getting started with Flutter&lt;/a&gt;. To recap, I spent some time learning about Flutter and writing Dart code, set up a really basic app, found a weather API that gave me the data I wanted and figured out how the parse the data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Delving straight into Flutter to try and code the main functionality of my Rain Checker app was really fun! I started off a bit freely but after messing around for half a day with trying to get a settings page and an autocompleting location search going I realised that I really should be working on the core functionality i.e. getting notifications to fire when it detects that its going to rain. Pretty much every app has notifications so it should be pretty simple to get working right? Wrong!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;why-arent-these-notifications-working&quot;&gt;Why aren’t these notifications working?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I started off on the wrong foot because I had somehow got the idea that the notifications that pop up on the top of your screen are called push notifications. It turns out they’re called push notifications when they’re pushed to your device by a server! This led me down a giant rabbit hole of setting up &lt;a href=&quot;https://firebase.google.com/&quot;&gt;Firebase Cloud Messaging&lt;/a&gt; and trying to figure out how to integrate with my rain forecasting code so it would prepare to issue a notification every day but cancel if it wasn’t going to rain.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;After eventually giving up on Firebase I decided to get the &lt;a href=&quot;https://pub.dev/packages/flutter_local_notifications&quot;&gt;Flutter Local Notifications package&lt;/a&gt; working which was way harder than I expected because the readme was quite confusing and the different articles and Youtube videos about it all seemed to implement it in a slightly different way. After managing to get scheduled notifications working I realised that I wouldn’t be able to both run my rain checking code and issue a notification when the app wasn’t active.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Finally after a helpful StackOverflow post I combined the Flutter Local Notifications package with the &lt;a href=&quot;https://pub.dev/packages/workmanager&quot;&gt;Flutter workmanager package&lt;/a&gt; which was finally able to send the notifications I wanted. Slight problem though - sometimes it would work properly and other times it wouldn’t. It was time-consuming to test scheduled notifications because workmanager has a minimum periodicity of 15 minutes, but eventually I was able to iron out all the issues in my code to get it working consistently. I had an idea for an app to help developers test scheduled notifications by changing the datetime of the device at a specific rate - maybe for my next app!&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;My notifications have broken a few times as I’ve tweaked the rest of my code but so far everything’s been a quick and simple fix&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;lessons-learned&quot;&gt;Lessons learned:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Flutter is still quite new so quite often I run into issues that there really isn’t much support out there. The Github issues page for the packages was quite useful though&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;There was a lot of value in running the example code myself and reading into how different things are implemented to get more familiar with how the package worked&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;When trying to debug a complicated issue a structured approach is really important i.e. change one thing at a time and re-test after each change&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Workmanager itself has some limitations - notifications often don’t fire at the exact time its scheduled&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;10-15-hours-later&quot;&gt;10-15 hours+ later:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/jUb1S3Pad19B9lhS3WslEcPiXFhGNhaqZ6znRG8TelE9nDfuEKmQrwWicqS7R9xX810B2bTtFrQZ7T4dFLS2mjQA5P_HD5BsHP0blUU71kHHnqTk6TfMKLuVBvVrRGJH4il68GuDA1aGzp6NYGK_lJd2V9gDwTBS4SXiZh9uIFhA-eIdcsR1YAhiSUHejAJUId-PyZReILERb9YZCTktMYQ_uOKCaFn3Q7q3Kzom5mBsSU33m7jSJ5jjr-1IBuCNBR8NlLkkTX4wnBw15plMLLYuPq4u_199fTNOnnopWhjDliaZWi5aQB35mn3x_oDTKXklkC3Wl6NSeJgIw0v2ZR1n5jHuKciOJuXgqkSqN4WYJ7wz7OYOoWLl6XA77isxOUVLFwFlAJk_Tuu3658E9lak4RBbj5yy2fOwXWdmh6VXQ_Uj_bpVsQtn0SO_OcftXSkfu9N8psK-J95Hlz_F9D8kGsYpJR6oFuTrcVXl71x-YF7ahxcoVQ0EKCWQFjtSVey2olTL1cYRvljCRIWCZpyi9i-hHQ-VFJ6taKC0doeN3Qh0ZvZA9sqL0GINugLz6Zcd1XFyRclpFGNK7gs2246XKjnlX8exQSWy01GA1PVpPAdpvd_cJ05R6VSv1r1P9zLXe4x44rpdxym4m_ipgX65TWloeUxzd2nSogvtSKvV7XlWKcLBJX51f1s4Vy8=w422-h937-no?authuser=0&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">This is Part 2 of my posts about learning Flutter. For Part 1 see my post about getting started with Flutter. To recap, I spent some time learning about Flutter and writing Dart code, set up a really basic app, found a weather API that gave me the data I wanted and figured out how the parse the data.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">HealthHack 2020</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/learning/cs/2020/08/02/healthhack.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="HealthHack 2020" /><published>2020-08-02T17:19:03+10:00</published><updated>2020-08-02T17:19:03+10:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/learning/cs/2020/08/02/healthhack</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/learning/cs/2020/08/02/healthhack.html">&lt;p&gt;Over the last two weekends I took part in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.healthhack.com.au/&quot;&gt;HealthHack 2020&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-did-i-end-up-getting-involved&quot;&gt;How did I end up getting involved?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was talking to a friend (shoutout to Jason Lim!) about my progress in learning computer science and he mentioned that some people have been running COVID-19 hackathons. I looked up hackathons but most had either been cancelled during COVID-19 or were exclusively for university students. HealthHack was pretty accessible and it was even fully virtual so it was low commitment&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-did-i-hope-to-get-out-of-it&quot;&gt;What did I hope to get out of it?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wanted to experience what a hackathon was like - I wasn’t confident in my technical abilities but hoped to do a bit of coding and also experience what it’s like to work in a team to develop software to solve a problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-was-the-experience-like&quot;&gt;What was the experience like?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I almost backed out during the first night but I found the perfect team:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The problem owner was a former HealthHack organiser so I felt like that’d be a good team for someone new to hackathons&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The problem owner was looking to implement a fairly low tech solution and wasn’t looking for any particularly strong software development skills&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The problem (how to help researchers better communicate their research to the public) was pretty close to something I’ve been thinking about (how to help the public better understand research and news articles citing research)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I had some great team members with a wide variety of backgrounds who were also beginners at coding&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other teams made some amazing things! Even though I think my team fell short in terms of a final polished solution I’m glad I chose them because:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I learnt a lot about the product design side of software engineering i.e. the user journey, identifying and addresss pain points, brainstorming and ideation&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I felt like I was able to make some meaningful contributions from a coding perspective.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-did-i-enjoy&quot;&gt;What did I enjoy?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I really enjoyed the process of writing Google Apps Scripts to try and link all our spreadsheets, docs and forms together. There was a lot of problem solving done and I got a lot of JavaScript practice&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I liked the event being virtual. It minimised the disruption to my weekends - I could easily hop off to do other things or multitask them. I’ve also always been terrible with presentations so it made that experience much less painful.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I liked how collaborative and non-competitive the event was - having no prizes was definitely a great idea&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-did-i-not-enjoy&quot;&gt;What did I not enjoy?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I was surprised by both the abundant supply and demand of software engineers. Most of the problems specifically asked for team members with UX design or front end / back end software development skills. The majority of people seemed to fall in this category with the remaining working in health-related industries so I felt like a bit of an outsider.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;There were a few instances where I thought that we were talking things to death or ideas were being brought up for the 10th time that just made me zone out form the discussion&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Two weekends is a pretty big commitment of time and I think the lack of time pressure made everything happen pretty slowly&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;would-i-do-it-again&quot;&gt;Would I do it again?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Yes! I would do HealthHack or another hackathon again in the future&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I would want to develop my technical skills further so I feel less constrained in the problems I can choose and the contributions I can make. Ideally I’d like to have some experience working as a software engineer first.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;However it would depend if there’s a problem that I feel passionate about&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Over the last two weekends I took part in HealthHack 2020!</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Is Catan a game of luck?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/misc/2020/07/26/catan.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Is Catan a game of luck?" /><published>2020-07-26T17:19:03+10:00</published><updated>2020-07-26T17:19:03+10:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/misc/2020/07/26/catan</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/misc/2020/07/26/catan.html">&lt;p&gt;I don’t even remember why I bought a board game or why I chose Catan but it holds a special place in my heart as the first board game I ever bought for myself. I’ve played a lot of other board games since then but Catan one of those games that I always find myself going back to! A decent online Catan platform called Colonist.io has popped up recently and playing some more competitive games with my friends has really inspired me to read more strategy and reflect on why some of my friends enjoy it and some don’t.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;a-game-of-luck-or-a-game-of-skill&quot;&gt;A game of luck or a game of skill?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most common complaint that I hear about the game is that there is too much luck involved. I’ve always accepted that there is a luck element involved in the game but I don’t agree that there is too much - there’s a reason that some of my friends never win and others win a lot. From my experiences the players that don’t enjoy the game generally do one of two things:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;they don’t put their starting settlements in good spots&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;they don’t trade during the game&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It makes sense from this perspective because without these you’re really at the complete mercy of the dice rolls. I’ve definitely found myself in games where I’m in a really bad position and it feels like a chore to play because I took a risk that flopped and I have no real chance of winning unless I get perfect dice rolls. The important thing is know how to both secure yourself a strong position and take the initiative to trade so that you’re not relying on luck to win. I watched some commentary from a pro player who thought that with perfect play the luck factor is about 20% which I agree with. I’ll accept that there are some players that don’t want to strategize and think about how to secure a stronger position, but for those that are even a little interested, here are some tips:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;beginner-tips&quot;&gt;Beginner tips:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Are there better spots with more dots? 11-13 dots is ideal&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Do you have any tiles with 6 or 8? these will usually get rolled the most often after 7&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;No wheat means defeat - you need it for everything except roads&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Wood and brick are useless unless you have both&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Can you build to a port at some point in the game?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Try to aim for either longest road or largest army&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;intermediate-tips&quot;&gt;Intermediate tips:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You don’t need every resource - Ore / Wheat / Sheep is a popular strategy&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;There are only 3 brick 3 ore tiles - if you want to secure good numbers on either resource, plan ahead&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Don’t get longest road early - it’s easy to take from you and you’ll get targeted&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Do you have a variety of numbers? if you’re stacking up on numbers you’re more reliant on dice rolls&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Look at the entire board and think about which resources are scarce&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Adapt your strategy to what position you are in - 4th player may not access to a resource if it’s scarce&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Before you place your first settlement, consider what options you will likely have for your second settlement&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;advanced-tips&quot;&gt;Advanced tips:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Can you place a settlement to lock the players after you out of a resource entirely?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;There’s no point securing yourself strong setup if it means other players have a better setup&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Look at what resources other players will aim for with their second settlement - consider placing defensively to block the spots they will want to place on&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If you’re 4th position avoid placing on the coast because this will give the other players more options for their second settlement&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Think about who will want to trade with you and what resources they will have too much of&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Consider the likelihood that a tile will be blocked during the game&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I don’t even remember why I bought a board game or why I chose Catan but it holds a special place in my heart as the first board game I ever bought for myself. I’ve played a lot of other board games since then but Catan one of those games that I always find myself going back to! A decent online Catan platform called Colonist.io has popped up recently and playing some more competitive games with my friends has really inspired me to read more strategy and reflect on why some of my friends enjoy it and some don’t.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Getting started with Flutter</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/learning/cs/2020/07/19/flutter.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Getting started with Flutter" /><published>2020-07-19T17:19:03+10:00</published><updated>2020-07-19T17:19:03+10:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/learning/cs/2020/07/19/flutter</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/learning/cs/2020/07/19/flutter.html">&lt;p&gt;When I was brainstorming ideas for personal projects to work on, I thought about trying to make my own mobile app. Wanting to start with something simple, I decided to make a weather app - with a twist! I’ve used weather apps and widgets in the past but I normally find myself uninstalling them because the weather in Sydney is pretty stable and most of the time I don’t care about the weather. The only time I really care about the weather is when it’s going to rain that day and I should probably bring an umbrella. It sounded simple enough - do absolutely nothing except tell me when it’s going to rain that day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-to-get-started&quot;&gt;How to get started?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I read some advice that a good way of being motivated to work on projects is to try and use new languages/technologies that you have to learn. I agree! I heard a friend talking about Flutter a while ago and this was the perfect opportunity to learn it. My usual routine of googling and searching through reddit for recommendations of learning resources led me to &lt;a href=&quot;https://flutter.dev/docs/get-started/install&quot;&gt;the official documentation&lt;/a&gt;, which is actually quite good. Overall it was easy to follow and quite clear, but:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Be prepared for some pretty huge file downloads&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I ran into a frustrating issue related to the Java JDK version that took me a few hours of attempted debugging before I gave up and posted an &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/flutter/flutter/issues/61354&quot;&gt;an issue on Github&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I watched a few introduction to Flutter videos on Youtube as well, but some of them were outdated and referenced older documentation. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=DIn-4nRfkUg&quot;&gt;This&lt;/a&gt; was probably the best video I found - made pretty recently and long but quite easy to follow at 2x speed. There are only a few videos on Youtube but App Brewery partnered with the Google Flutter team to provide the first half of the course for free &lt;a href=&quot;https://flutter.dev/freecourse&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;! The course is really good at explaining the concepts such that even a beginner could follow along but a more experienced programmer might find some of the lessons pretty trivial. I ended up following closely along with the first few chapters and then skimming through the rest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;a-lot-of-tinkering&quot;&gt;A lot of tinkering&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I read through the Dart documentation as well, but didn’t spend too much time there because it seemed pretty similar to Java. The main differences so far are things that I’ve seen in other languages like JavaScript, or syntactic sugar. I knew that the core of my app would be a weather API that provided data for probability of precipitation (PoP), so I started with a search for that. Unfortunately the Flutter weather package uses OpenWeather’s API which didn’t include PoP, but there is a http package that I could use. It was surprisingly difficult to find a weather API that was both free and included PoP, but after a long search I discovered &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.weatherbit.io/&quot;&gt;weatherbit.io&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point I sat down and wrote myself a list of:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What functionalities I wanted the app to have&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What settings I wanted the app to have&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What problems I expected to have to tackle&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A rough outline of the steps I expected to work through&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As of now I’ve got a pretty rudimentary app set-up and I’m able to extract the PoP data but I have a lot of work to go. It’ll be interesting to look back at my progress after I’m done and see how I could have made it easier for me!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://firebasestorage.googleapis.com/v0/b/firescript-577a2.appspot.com/o/imgs%2Fapp%2FAndyNotes%2F2hxJgcX9w4.png?alt=media&amp;amp;token=3863a8b5-5f96-4d84-8907-67708282b792&quot; width=&quot;520&quot; height=&quot;750&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://firebasestorage.googleapis.com/v0/b/firescript-577a2.appspot.com/o/imgs%2Fapp%2FAndyNotes%2F-nSX0JjSQN.png?alt=media&amp;amp;token=fd6ae0e1-14b0-45c4-9af5-9f4887669a81&quot; width=&quot;308&quot; height=&quot;646&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">When I was brainstorming ideas for personal projects to work on, I thought about trying to make my own mobile app. Wanting to start with something simple, I decided to make a weather app - with a twist! I’ve used weather apps and widgets in the past but I normally find myself uninstalling them because the weather in Sydney is pretty stable and most of the time I don’t care about the weather. The only time I really care about the weather is when it’s going to rain that day and I should probably bring an umbrella. It sounded simple enough - do absolutely nothing except tell me when it’s going to rain that day.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Algorithms</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/learning/cs/2020/07/12/algorithms.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Algorithms" /><published>2020-07-12T17:19:03+10:00</published><updated>2020-07-12T17:19:03+10:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/learning/cs/2020/07/12/algorithms</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/learning/cs/2020/07/12/algorithms.html">&lt;p&gt;My biggest takeaway from the Princeton Algorithms course (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.coursera.org/learn/algorithms-part1/home/welcome&quot;&gt;Part 1&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.coursera.org/learn/algorithms-part2/home/welcome&quot;&gt;Part 2&lt;/a&gt;) was an appreciation for why knowledge about data structures and algorithms (DSAs) is so important to software design. An idea that the course hits on several times throughout these courses is that the choice of a faster DSA can be significantly more impactful to the performance of a progam compared to improvements in hardware or increasing the amount of computing power utilised.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;do-i-even-need-this-information-on-the-job&quot;&gt;Do I even need this information on the job?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Throughout the course, I would wonder things like:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Do I really need to know how left-leaning red black trees work?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Do I really need to know how to implement the Knuth-Morris Pratt algorithm?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The general consensus from talking to friends and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/cscareerquestions/comments/ho0o5l/how_data_structure_and_algorithm_is_actually_used/&quot;&gt;Reddit&lt;/a&gt; seems to be that knowing how to specifically implement different DSAs isn’t necessary, but knowledge about their properties and impact on time and complexity can be quite important. The course is definitely aware of this and provides you with implementations for almost every DSA it teaches, while still making sure to walk through their properties and how they would be implemented in Java.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe others would even find themselves interested in the field of algorithmic research - the course has a lot of great historical context on how we developed the DSAs in use today and what could potentially be developed in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;am-i-ready-for-interviews-now&quot;&gt;Am I ready for interviews now?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Completing the course doesn’t make me feel like I’m ready for interviews, but I feel like I’ve built the foundation for the rest of my study. I can’t remember how to implement a heap sort or DFS at the moment, but it’s going to be much much easier when I review that again one day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;DSAs weren’t something that I really thought about right up until I started working through Leetcode problems and my naive approaches weren’t quite cutting it. I’d encounter medium difficulty problems and feel like pieces of the puzzle were missing. I feel like I have most of those missing puzzle pieces now. I’m looking forward to putting some time into Leetcode seeing how much I’ve progressed - but that’ll have to wait for a future post.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">My biggest takeaway from the Princeton Algorithms course (Part 1 and Part 2) was an appreciation for why knowledge about data structures and algorithms (DSAs) is so important to software design. An idea that the course hits on several times throughout these courses is that the choice of a faster DSA can be significantly more impactful to the performance of a progam compared to improvements in hardware or increasing the amount of computing power utilised.</summary></entry></feed>